Twenty-three years ago,
قبل 23 عامًا،
at the age of 19,
في عمر الـ 19،
I shot and killed a man.
أطلقت النار وقتلت شخصًا.
I was a young drug dealer
كنت مُروج مخدرات يافع
with a quick temper
بمزاج متقلب
and a semi-automatic pistol.
ومسدس شبه أوتوماتيكي.
But that wasn't the end of my story.
ولكن تلك لم تكن نهاية قصتي.
and the 23 years since
ومنذ 23 سنة
is a story of acknowledgment,
هي قصة إقرار
apology and atonement.
واعتذار وتكفير.
But it didn't happen in the way
لكنها لم تحدث بالطريقة
that you might imagine or think.
التي يمكن لك أن تتصورها أو تعتقدها.
These things occurred in my life
تلك الأشياء حدث في حياتي
in a way that was surprising,
بطريقة كانت مفاجئة،
especially to me.
خصوصًا لي.
See, like many of you,
مثل العديد منكم،
growing up, I was an honor roll student,
لدى نشأتي، كنت طالبا مثاليا،
a scholarship student,
طالبا بمنحة،
with dreams of becoming a doctor.
يحلم بأن يُصبح طبيبا.
when my parents separated
عندما انفصل والداي
and eventually divorced.
وفي النهاية تطلقا.
At the age of 17,
في عمر الـ17،
I got shot three times
تعرضت للإصابة ثلاثة مرات
standing on the corner of my block in Detroit.
كنت واقفًا في ناصية مباني بديترويت.
My friend rushed me to the hospital.
صديقي أسرع بي إلى المستشفى.
Doctors pulled the bullets out,
قام الطبيب بإخراج الرصاص،
patched me up,
وقطب جرحي،
Throughout this ordeal,
طوال هذه المحنة،
no one hugged me,
لم يحتضني أحد،
no one counseled me,
لم يرشدني أحد،
no one told me I would be okay.
لم يخبرني أحد بأني سأكون بخير.
No one told me that I would live in fear,
لم يخبرني أحد أنني سوف أعيش في خوف،
that I would become paranoid,
وأني سأصبح مرتابا،
to being shot.
لأني أُصبت.
No one told me that one day,
لم يخبرني أحد أنه يومًا ما،
I would become the person behind the trigger.
سأصبح الشخص الذي أطلق الزناد.
Fourteen months later,
لاحقًا بعد 14 شهرًا،
at 2 a.m.,
في الساعة 2 صباحًا،
I fired the shots
أطلقت النار
When I entered prison,
عندما دخلت السجن،
I was bitter, I was angry, I was hurt.
كنت مريرًا وكنت غاضبًا وكنت مجروحًا.
I didn't want to take responsibility.
لم أُرد أن أتحمل المسئولية.
I blamed everybody from my parents
وألقيت اللوم علي كل شخص ابتداء من أهلي
to the system.
إلى الحكومة.
I rationalized my decision to shoot
سوغت قراري بإطلاق النار
because in the hood where I come from,
بأن المنطقة التي أتيت منها،
it's better to be the shooter
من الأفضل أن تكون الجاني
than the person getting shot.
على أن تكون المجني عليه.
As I sat in my cold cell,
أثناء مكوثي في زنزاتي الباردة،
I felt helpless,
شعرت بالعجز،
unloved and abandoned.
وبأنني غير محبوب ومهجور.
I felt like nobody cared,
شعرت بأنه لا أحد يهتم،
and I reacted
وكانت ردة فعلي
with hostility to my confinement.
عِدائية تجاه حبسي.
And I found myself getting
ووجدت نفسي أتعمق
deeper and deeper into trouble.
أكثر وأكثر في المشاكل.
I ran black market stores,
أدرت متاجر للسوق السوداء،
I loan sharked,
كُنت أتعامل بالربا،
and I sold drugs that were illegally smuggled
وأبيع المخدرات التي أُهربها بطريقة غير شرعية
into the prison.
إلى داخل السجن.
what the warden of the Michigan Reformatory called
ما يدعوني به آمر السجن بإصلاحية ميشيغان
"the worst of the worst."
"أسوأ السيئين".
I landed in solitary confinement
انتهى بي الأمر بالحبس الانفرادي
for seven and a half years
لمدة سبع سنوات ونصف
out of my incarceration.
من مدة حبسي.
Now as I see it, solitary confinement
رؤيتي للحبس الانفرادي
is one of the most inhumane and barbaric places
هو أنه واحد من أكثر الأماكن اللاإنسانية والهمجية
you can find yourself,
التي يمكنك أن تجدها،
but find myself I did.
ولكني وجدتها.
One day, I was pacing my cell,
في أحد الأيام، كنت أخطو داخل زنزانتي،
when an officer came and delivered mail.
عندها جاء ضابط وسلمني البريد.
I looked at a couple of letters
نظرت إلى بضعة رسائل
before I looked at the letter
قبل أن أنظر إلى الرسالة
that had my son's squiggly handwriting on it.
التي كانت بخط ابني المتعرج.
And anytime I would get a letter from my son,
ومنذ مدة كنت أود الحصول على رسالة من ابني،
it was like a ray of light
كانت مثل شعاع من الضوء
in the darkest place you can imagine.
في أحلك مكان يمكن تخيله.
And on this particular day, I opened this letter,
وفي هذا اليوم بالذات، فتحت هذا الخطاب،
and in capital letters, he wrote,
وفي استهلاليته كتب،
"My mama told me why you was in prison:
"أمي أخبرتني لماذا أنت في السجن:
murder."
بسبب جريمة قتل"
He said, "Dad, don't kill.
وقال: " أبي، لا تقتل
Jesus watches what you do. Pray to Him."
يسوع يراقب ما تفعله. صلي له".
Now, I wasn't religious at that time,
حينها لم أكن ذلك الشخص المتدين،
nor am I religious now,
كما أنني لست متدينًا الآن،
but it was something so profound
ولكنه كان شيء عميقًا جدًا
about my son's words.
بخصوص كلمات إبني.
They made me examine things about my life
لقد جعلتني أتفحص الأشياء الموجودة بحياتي
that I hadn't considered.
التي لم آخذها بعين الأعتبار.
It was the first time in my life
تلك كانت المرة الأولى في حياتي
that I had actually thought about the fact
التي قمت فيها بالتفكير في حقيقة
that my son would see me as a murderer.
أن ابني سوف يراني كقاتل.
I sat back on my bunk
جلست للوراء في سرير نومي
and I reflected on something I had read
وتأملت في شيء كنت قد قرأته
in [Plato],
عن [أفلاطون]
where Socrates stated in "Apology"
حيث ذكر سقراط في "الاعتذار"
that the unexamined life isn't worth living.
أن الحياة من دون اختبارات لا تستحق العيش.
But it didn't come easy.
لكنه لم يكن سهل المنال.
which was part of the transformation,
التي كانت جزء من التحول،
was that there were four key things.
أن هنالك أربعة أمور أساسية.
The first thing was,
الأمر الأول كان،
I had great mentors.
لدي مرشدون عظماء.
how did you find a great mentor in prison?
كيف لك أن تجد مرشدين عظماء في السجن؟
But in my case,
ولكن في حالتي،
some of my mentors
بعض المرشدين
who are serving life sentences
الذين يقضون عقوبة السجن المؤبد
were some of the best people to ever come into my life,
كانوا من أفضل الأشخاص الذين تواجدوا بحياتي،
and they forced me to challenge myself
وأجبروني على تحدي نفسي
about my decision making.
لاتخاذ قرارتي.
Prior to going to prison,
في الماضي قبل دخولي السجن،
I didn't know that there were so many brilliant
لم أكن أعرف أن هناك عباقرة كثر
black poets, authors and philosophers,
من الشعراء السود والمؤلفين والفلاسفة،
of encountering Malcolm X's autobiography,
في أن أطلع على السيرة الذاتية لمالكوم إكس،
and it shattered every stereotype I had about myself.
وبعثر ذلك الصورة التقليدية التي أكنها لنفسي.
The third thing was family.
كان الأمر الثالث هو الأسرة.
For 19 years, my father stood by my side
لمدة 19 عاما، وقف والدي إلى جانبي
with an unshakable faith,
بإيمان لا يتزعزع،
because he believed that I had what it took
لأنه يؤمن أن لدي المقومات
to turn my life around.
لتغيير مجرى حياتي.
I also met an amazing woman
كما تعرفت على امرأة رائعة
who is now the mother of my two-year-old son Sekou,
والتي هي الآن والدة إبني سيكو البالغ عامين من العمر،
and she taught me how to love myself
وعلمتني كيف أحب نفسي
in a healthy way.
بطريقة مفيدة.
The final thing was writing.
الأمر الأخير كان الكتابة.
When I got that letter from my son,
عندما حصلت على تلك الرسالة من ابني،
I began to write a journal
بدأت في كتابة يوميات
about things I had experienced in my childhood
عن الأشياء التي مررت بها في طفولتي
and in prison,
وفي السجن،
and what it did is it opened up my mind to the idea
وذلك قد فتح عقلي لفكرة
Earlier in my incarceration, I had received
سابقًا في فترة احتجازي، كنت قد تلقيت
a letter from one of the relatives of my victim,
رسالة من أحد أقارب الضحية،
and in that letter,
كان موفد الرسالة،
she told me she forgave me,
أنها قد سامحتني،
because she realized I was a young child
لانها لاحظت أنني فتى
who had been abused
قد تعرضت للإساءة
and had been through some hardships
وأنه قد مرت بي بعض المحن
and just made a series of poor decisions.
وأدي ذلك إلى سلسلة من القرارت الخاطئة.
It was the first time in my life
كانت تلك المرة الأولي بحياتي
One of the things that happened
واحدة من الأشياء التي حدثت
after that experience is that
بعد تلك التجربة هو أنني
I thought about the other men who were incarcerated
فكرت في الرجال الآخرين الذين كانوا محبوسين
alongside of me,
إلى جانبي،
and how much I wanted to share this with them.
وكم أردت أن أشاطرهذا معهم.
And so I started talking to them about
وأيضًا التحدث معهم عن
some of their experiences,
بعض تجاربهم،
and I was devastated to realize
وشعرت بحزن لإدراكي
that most of them came from the same abusive environments,
أن معظمهم جاؤوا من نفس البيئات المسيئة،
And most of them wanted help and they wanted to turn it around,
ومعظمهم من يريد المساعدة ويريدون التغيير،
but unfortunately the system
ولكن للأسف الحكومة
that currently holds 2.5 million people in prison
التي تحتجز حاليًا 2.5 مليون شخص في السجن
is designed to warehouse
تهدف إلى مجرد الاستيعاب
as opposed to rehabilitate or transform.
بدلا من إعادة التأهيل أو التحويل.
So I made it up in my mind
لذا خطرت في بالى فكرة
that if I was ever released from prison
أنه إذا تم إطلاق سراحي من السجن
that I would do everything in my power
فإنني سأبذل قصارى جهدي
to help change that.
للمساعدة بتغيير ذلك.
In 2010, I walked out of prison
في 2010 خرجت من السجن
for the first time after two decades.
لأول مرة عقب عقدين من الزمن.
Now imagine, if you will,
الآن تخيل، إذا صح التعبير،
Fred Flintstone walking into an episode
فريد فلينتستون داخل حلقة
of "The Jetsons."
لـ "ذا جتسونز".
That was pretty much what my life was like.
ذلك إلى حد كبير ما كان يشابه حياتي.
For the first time, I was exposed to the Internet,
للمرة الأولى، أتعرف على شبكة الإنترنت،
social media,
والوسائط الاجتماعية،
cars that talk like KITT from "Knight Rider."
والسيارات التي تتحدث مثل كيت من "نايت رايدر"
But the thing that fascinated me the most
ولكن الشيء الذي كنت مفتونًا به أكثر
was phone technology.
كانت تكنولوجيا الهواتف.
See, when I went to prison,
ترى، عندما دخلت إلى السجن،
our car phones were this big
كانت هواتف السيارت بهذا الحجم
and required two people to carry them.
وتتطلب شخصين لحملها.
So imagine what it was like when I first grabbed
لذا تخيل كيف كان الأمر عند حملي لأول مرة
my little Blackberry
هاتفي البلاكبيري الصغير
and I started learning how to text.
ولقد بدأت بتعلم كيفية كتابة الرسائل النصية.
But the thing is, the people around me,
ولكن الأمر هو، الناس من حولي،
they didn't realize that I had no idea
لم يدركوا أنني لم تكن لدي أدني فكرة
what all these abbreviated texts meant,
ما الذي تعنيه كل هذه النصوص المختصرة،
like LOL, OMG, LMAO,
مثل: LOL, OMG, LMAO،
until one day I was having a conversation
حتى في يوم ما كنت أُحادث
with one of my friends via text,
واحدا من أصدقائي عبر الرسائل النصية،
And I was like, "What is K?"
فقلت، "ما هو K؟"
And he was like, "K is okay."
وكان رده "K تعني أوكي".
So in my head, I was like,
لذلك في رأسي، كنت أقول،
"Well what the hell is wrong with K?"
"حسنا ما هي بحق الجحيم مشكلة K؟"
And so I text him a question mark.
ولذا أرسلت له علامة استفهام.
And he said, "K = okay."
وقال: "K = أوكي"
And so I tap back, "FU." (Laughter)
ولذا نقرت كاتبا "FU". (ضحك)
And then he texts back, and he asks me
ثم أرسل لي مستعلمًا
why was I cussing him out.
لماذا قمت بشتمه.
And I said, "LOL FU,"
وقلت، "LOL FU"،
as in, I finally understand.
بطبيعة الحال فهمت في النهاية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I'm doing relatively good.
أفعالي كانت جيدة نسبيًا.
I have a fellowship at MIT Media Lab,
لدي زمالة في مختبر الوسائط بمعهد ماساتشوستس للتكنولوجيا،
I work for an amazing company called BMe,
أنا أعمل في شركة مذهلة تسمى BMe،
I teach at the University of Michigan,
أقوم بالتدريس في جامعة ميشيغان،
but it's been a struggle
ولكنه كان صراعا
because I realize that there are more
لأنني أدرك أن هناك المزيد
men and women coming home
من الرجال والنساء عائدين إلى منازلهم
who are not going to be afforded those opportunities.
ولم تكن لتتاح لهم تلك الفرص.
I've been blessed to work with some amazing
لقد أُنعم علي بالعمل مع مجموعة مذهلة
men and women,
من الرجال والنساء،
helping others reenter society,
يُساعدون الآخرين على العودة للمجتمع،
and one of them is my friend named Calvin Evans.
واحد منهم هو صديق لي يدعى كالفين ايفانز.
He served 24 years for a crime he didn't commit.
حُبس لـ 24 عاما لجريمة لم يرتكبها.
He's 45 years old. He's currently enrolled in college.
لديه 45 سنة التحق حالياُ بالجامعة.
And one of the things that we talked about
أحد الأشياء التي تحدثنا عنها
is the three things that I found important
بخصوص الأشياء الثلاثة التي وجدتها مهمة
in my personal transformation,
في تحول شخصيتي،
the first being acknowledgment.
أولها الإقرار.
I had to acknowledge that I had hurt others.
وجب علي الاقرار بأنني آذيت آخرين.
I also had to acknowledge that I had been hurt.
وأود أيضا أن أُقر بأنني تآذيت.
The second thing was apologizing.
الشيء الثاني كان الاعتذار.
I had to apologize to the people I had hurt.
وجب علي أن أعتذر للذين آذيتهم.
Even though I had no expectations of them accepting it,
على الرغم من أنني لم أتوقع منهم القبول،
it was important to do because it was the right thing.
كان من المهم فعل ذلك لأنه الصواب.
But I also had to apologize to myself.
ولكن أيضا يجب أن أعتذر لنفسي.
The third thing was atoning.
الشيء الثالث كان التكفير.
For me, atoning meant
بالنسبة لي، يعني التكفير
going back into my community
العودة إلى مجتمعي
and working with at-risk youth
والعمل مع الشباب المعرضين للخطر
who were on the same path,
الذين كانوا في المسار نفسه،
but also becoming at one with myself.
لكن أيضًا أن أتحد مع نفسي.
Through my experience of being locked up,
من خلال تجربتي في السجن،
one of the things I discovered is this:
واحدة من الأشياء التي اكتشفتها هي:
the majority of men and women
غالبية الرجال والنساء
who are incarcerated are redeemable,
المسجونين سيعودون إليه مجددًا،
and the fact is,
وفي الواقع فإن،
90 percent of the men and women who are incarcerated
90 في المئة من الرجال والنساء الذين سجنوا
will at some point return to the community,
سيعودون في وقت ما إلى مجتمعهم،
and we have a role in determining what kind
ونحن لدينا الدور في تحديد أي نوع
of men and women return to our community.
من العائدين إلي مجتمعنا من الرجال والنساء.
My wish today
أمنيتي اليوم
a more empathetic approach
نهجا أكثر تعاطفًا
toward how we deal with mass incarceration,
في كيفية التعامل مع السجن الجماعي،
that we will do away with
أن نستغني من
the lock-them-up-and-throw-away-the-key mentality,
عقلية "الإغلاق ورمي المفتاح بعيدا"،
because it's proven it doesn't work.
لأنه ثبُت أن هذا لا يُجدي.
My journey is a unique journey,
رحلتي هي حالة فريدة من نوعها،
but it doesn't have to be that way.
وليس من الضروري أن تكون علي هذا المنوال.
Anybody can have a transformation
أي شخص يمكنه التحول
if we create the space for that to happen.
إذا هيئنا الظروف المناسبة لحدوث ذلك.
So what I'm asking today
لذا ما أطلبه اليوم
is that you envision
هو تصور
a world where men and women
عالم يكون فيه الرجال والنساء
aren't held hostage to their pasts,
ليسوا رهائن لماضيهم،
where misdeeds and mistakes
حيث الآثام والأخطاء
don't define you for the rest of your life.
لن تحددك لبقية حياتك.
I think collectively, we can create that reality,
وأعتقد أننا معًا يمكننا خلق هذا الواقع،
and I hope you do too.
وآمل أن تفعلوا ذلك.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)